Guide to the Yun Gee Papers, 1907-1979 MSS.144
Fales Library and Special Collections
Yun Gee Papers
1907-1979
Fales Library and Special Collections
Gee, Helen
Gee, Yun, 1906-1963
MSS.144
6 Linear Feet in 7 boxes
Yun Gee (1906-1963) was a Chinese American modernist painter who was active in San Francisco, Paris, and later New York. The Yun Gee Papers includes correspondence, audiovisual material, scrapbooks, catalogues, and biographical information associated with Gee's art career. The collection covers the years 1907-1979.
Biographical Note
Yun Gee was a modernist painter of some acclaim. He was born in Gee Village (now called Chu Village) near Canton, China in 1906. At the age of 15, he arrived in San Francisco and enrolled in the San Francisco Art Institute (then called the California School of Fine Arts), where he studied under Gottardo Piazzoni and Otis Oldfield. In 1926, Gee turned his attention to avant-garde painting, renouncing his classical training. He went to Paris to pursue his career. It was there that he met and married Princess Paule de Reuss. Gee befriended Gertrude Stein and became involved in bohemian circles concerned with poetry and Cubist painting.
Gee moved to New York City in the early 1930s, where he exhibited in major galleries in New York City, including the Museum of Modern Art and the Brooklyn Museum. In 1942, he married Helen Charlotte Wimmer. Although they divorced in 1947, Helen Gee kept her married name and later worked to promote Yun Gee's career after his death. In San Francisco, Paris, and New York, Gee was often the first or only Chinese artist to show in major galleries, and was the target of prejudice and discrimination in the art world all his life.
Sources: http://www.nyu-apastudies.org/2012/the-yun-gee-papers/ http://www.yungee.com/constructedsite/chron.html
Scope and Contents
The Yun Gee Papers comprises correspondence, personal papers, art catalogues, scrapbooks, audiovisual material, and biographical information related to Gee's art career.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement
The Yun Gee Papers are organized into five series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Scrapbooks
Series III: Biographical
Series IV: Media
Series V: Books
Within each series, materials are arranged chronologically, when material is dated. In some cases, which are indicated, material organized by Helen Gee has retained its original organization.
Provenance
The papers were donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections by Yun Gee's first wife, gallerist Helen Gee, in 2001.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to their extreme fragility, access to selected scrapbooks is considered upon request. Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
San Francisco (Calif.); Scrapbooks.; Painters -- United States.; Correspondence.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Paris (France); Painting, American -- New York (State) -- New York.; Moving images.; Limelight (Gallery: New York, N.Y.); Asian American artists.; Clippings (information artifacts); Gee, Yun, 1906-1963; Gee, Helen; Reuss, Paule de
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Content
  This series contains letters to and from Gee, and includes letters from his first wife.
  - Paris, 1928-30, Letters from Paule de Reuss [1 of 2], 1928-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Paris, 1928-30, Letters from Paule de Reuss [2 of 2], 1928-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Divorce, [13 Rue Nicolo] 1930-, Letters from Paule de Reuss [1 of 3], 1930-, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Divorce, [13 Rue Nicolo] 1930-, Letters from Paule de Reuss [2 of 3], 1930-, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Divorce, [13 Rue Nicolo] 1930-, Letters from Paule de Reuss [3 of 3], 1930-, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Paule de Reuss, New York 1932-36 [1 of 3], 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Paule de Reuss, New York 1932-36 [2 of 3], 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Paule de Reuss, New York 1932-36 [3 of 3], 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Divorce Paper (Paule de Reuss, 1932), Gallery Correspondence (1940s), etc. [1 of 1], 1932-, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1936-, Yun in Paris, Letters from Paule de Reuss [1 of 4], 1936-, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1936-, Yun in Paris, Letters from Paule de Reuss [2 of 4], 1936-, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1936-, Yun in Paris, Letters from Paule de Reuss [3 of 4], 1936-, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1936-, Yun in Paris, Letters from Paule de Reuss [4 of 4], 1936-, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence [1 of 1], 1907, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New York, 40s-50s [1 of 1], 1940s-, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Scrapbooks
  This series contains scrapbooks with clippings of interest to Yun Gee, compiled during his time spent in Paris and New York.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the extreme fragility of this series, access to selected scrapbooks is considered upon request. For more information, contact a Fales archivist at fales.library@nyu.edu.
  - Loose scrapbook pages, 1930-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Due to the extreme fragility, access to this scrapbook is considered upon request. For more information, contact a Fales archivist at fales.library@nyu.edu.
  - Scrapbook, 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
  - Gee obituary clipping/1948 publication "Le Vivan", 1948-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 6-10)
  - Scrapbook, 1941-1943 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
  - Scrapbook: "New York Criticism" (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1943-1956 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 4-8)
- Series III: Biographical
  This series contains material about Yun Gee that was not generated by him personally, and includes an essay by his widow, clippings, and catalogs.
  - Helen Gee's Essay, Yun Gee Exhibition Catalog, Benton Museum 1979 [1 of 1] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Paintings of Yun Gee, William Benton Museum of Art, 1979 [1 of 1] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Yun Gee Review, American Artist, January 1974 [1 of 1] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Yun Gee Reviews, Arts Magazine, 1968 [1 of 1], May 1968, June/Summer 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Media
  This series contains a 16 mm black and white film reel of Yun Gee with accompanying 1/4 inch audio reels.
  Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - [Audio for Film of Yun Gee], Undated; cuid41190 (Box Shared Fales 106, Quarter inch audio reel ID: 144.0001)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 30 minutes; Preservation note: Captured in one pass, Track 1 caught in reverse and digitally corrected.
  - [Audio for Film of Yun Gee], Undated; cuid41192 (Box Shared Fales 106, Quarter inch audio reel cuid41192)
    Duration: 130 minutes; Preservation note: Captured in one pass, Track 1 caught in reverse and digitally corrected.
  - [Film of Yun Gee], Undated; cuid41191 (Box Shared Fales 099, 16mm film reels ID: 144.0002)
- Series V: Books
  This series contains five volumes donated with the collection.
  - Who's Who in China? Shanghai: The China Weekly Review, 1931. (Box 2)
  - Select Paintings and Sculpture from the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden. New York: Harry N. Abrams, 1974. (Box 2)
  - Gee, Helen, Limelight: A Greenwich Village Photography Gallery and Coffeehouse in the Fifties. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Nianci Zhou, Hua yi hua jie Zhu Yuanzhi .Taibei Shi: Fang zhi chu ban she, 1997., 1999 (Box 2)